<tool id="rsemQuantifyE3" name="EAP transcript quantification by RSEM" version="1.0">
    <description> (fastQ to bam)</description>
    <command interpreter="python">
        rsemQuantifyE3.py $bamInput $bamEval $geneResults $transcriptResults
        $genome $expType $repNo ${name}U${__user_id__}
    </command>
    <version_command>python ../../../../tools/encode/starAlignE3.py --version</version_command>
    <stdio>
        <exit_code range="1:" level="fatal" description="Fatal error" />
        <regex match=".*" source="stderr" level="log" />
    </stdio>
    <inputs>
        <param name="genome" type="select" label="Genome Assembly">
            <option value="hg19" selected="true">GRCh37/hg19 Human reference</option>
        </param>
        <param name="expType" type="select" label="Experiment Type">
            <option value="RNAseq-long" selected="true">long RNA-seq</option>
        </param>
        <param name="spike" type="select" label="Spike-In Control">
            <option value="ERCC" selected="true">ERCC/NIST/Ambion</option>
        </param>
        <param name="bamInput" type="data" label="Annotation bam (alignments file)" format="bam" />
        <param name="bamEval"  type="data" label="Genome bam Evaluation file (json)"
               format="txt" />
        <param name="repNo" type="integer" value="1" label="Replicate" min="0" help="Numbers only">
        </param>
        <param name="name" type="text" value="" size="40" optional="true" label="Analysis Name" 
               help="Letters and numbers only [optional]">
            <sanitizer invalid_char=""><valid initial="string.letters,string.digits"/></sanitizer>
        </param>
    </inputs>
    <outputs>
        <data format="txt" name="geneResults"
              label="Gene quantification ${name}Rep${repNo}" />
        <data format="txt" name="transcriptResults"
              label="Transcript quantification ${name}Rep${repNo}" />
    </outputs>
    <help>
.. class:: infomark

   Quantification of known transcripts found in the GENCODE annotation, performed by 'RSEM'. 
   An *ENCODE3 Analysis Pipeline* involves multiple steps and dataset replicates, of which this
   is one. Use *EAP workflows* to ensure that all analysis steps are performed in the proper
   sequence.

**Inputs:**
    All *Analysis Pipeline* steps require **Genome Assembly** and **Experiment Type**.  
    Currently only the GRCh37/hg19 reference genome is supported. Note that some steps are 
    only appropriate for some experiment types.
    
    All ENCODE long RNA-seq experiments are expected to include the ERCC/NIST/Ambion **Spike-In** 
    control set.  Spike-ins provide a method of normalization across experiments.
    
    The **Annotation bam** is the file of reads aligned to the gencode annotation.  This should 
    not be confused with its companion "genome bam: which contains alignments tothe whole genome.

    The **Genome bam Evaluation** file is required by this analysis step.  This evaluation file is 
    in json format generated from a previous *EAP bam evaluation* step.  NOTE that the 
    evaluation is of the companion "Genome bam" file and not the **Annotation bam** file 
    that is the major input to this step. 
    
    The **Replicate** number allows combining multiple replicates into a single analysis.  If the 
    replicate number is not incremented then repeated steps within the same named analysis will 
    overwrite previous step results.  Merged replicates should have a 0 (zero) replicate number. 
    
    The optional **Analysis Name** field will be used to tie multiple steps together into 
    one analysis, ensuring related files are well named and a single log records all processing 
    taken.  If the intention is to run multiple analyses, then providing an analysis name ensures 
    that results from one analyis are over-written by another.  Multiple histories for a single user 
    can share the same named analysis, but two separate users cannot.
    
**Outputs:**
    This step is expected to produce two files.  The results should reflect a gender neutral 
    annotation with ERCC spike-ins.  In other words, a female bio-sample run through the 
    long RNA-seq analysis will contain chrY gene results but they will be zero.  The two files are:
    
    - **Gene quantification** is a tab delimited quanitfication file, one line per gene.
    - **Transcript quantification** is a tab delimited quanitfication file, one line per transcript.

    The **log** of this single step can be seen under *view details* stdout.

    If the outputs are delivered to a location external to galaxy, the **Analysis log** covering 
    all steps of the analysis will be delivered to the same location.  Otherwise the log may be
    found in the directory pointed to by 'tmpDir' as defined in the settings file.

+--------+------------------------------------------------------------------------------------+
||encPng||All *ENCODE3 Analysis Pipeline* steps provided through Galaxy are run via the same  | 
|        |UCSC scripts and third-party tools as the official *Analysis Pipeline*.  Just as    | 
|        |with the official pipeline, all work is be performed in temporary directories and   |
|        |successful results moved to well-named locations.  If the initial input datasets are| 
|        |from a symlinked Galaxy library, results will be moved to the same directory as the |  
|        |inputs and then symlinked back into Galaxy. If the initial inputs do not have a     | 
|        |recognizable location outside the Galaxy database, then results will be written     |
|        |back into the Galaxy database as well.                                              |
+--------+------------------------------------------------------------------------------------+

.. |encPng| image:: http://genome.ucsc.edu/images/ENCODE_scaleup_logo.png
   :width: 100

    </help>
</tool>
